<!DOCTYPE html>
<html>
  <head>
    <meta charset='utf-8'>
    <!-- Always force latest IE rendering engine or request Chrome Frame -->
    <meta content='IE=edge,chrome=1' http-equiv='X-UA-Compatible'>
    <meta content='Gray Bike is a creative technology studio based in San Francisco, California.' name='description'>
    <meta content='software development, software engineering, engineering, design, consultancy, software consultancy, consulting, freelance, software developers, rails, d3, data visualization, data viz' name='keywords'>
    <meta content='width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0' name='viewport'>
    <meta content='mGFqkZIpRsu-KTICkZB_Lk453ig5zwNKhB2WrqWtqTg' name='google-site-verification'>
    <!-- Use title if it's in the page YAML frontmatter -->
    <title>Gray Bike</title>
    <link href='http://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Source+Sans+Pro:200,300,400,500,600,700,800' rel='stylesheet' type='text/css'>
    <link href="../stylesheets/all.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" />
    <script src='https://use.typekit.net/wqk5aml.js'></script>
    <script>
      try{Typekit.load({ async: true });}catch(e){}
    </script>
  </head>
  <body class='words words_feed'>
    <header>
      <div>
        <h2>
          <a href='/'>
            <span class='dg'>GRAY</span>BIKE
          </a>
        </h2>
      </div>
      <nav>
        <a href='/'>
          <span>About</span>
        </a>
        <a href='/work'>
          <span>Work</span>
        </a>
        <a href='/words'>
          <span class='active'>Words</span>
        </a>
      </nav>
    </header>
    <?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
    <feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
      <title>Blog Name</title>
      <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
      <id>http://blog.url.com/words</id>
      <link href="http://blog.url.com/words"/>
      <link href="http://blog.url.com/words/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
      <updated>2016-02-02T19:00:00-05:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Blog Author</name>
      </author>
      <entry>
        <title>Building Great Client Relationships</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/words/2016-02-03-building-great-client-relationships/"/>
        <id>http://blog.url.com/words/2016-02-03-building-great-client-relationships/</id>
        <published>2016-02-02T19:00:00-05:00</published>
        <updated>2017-09-19T16:09:05-04:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Article Author</name>
        </author>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been a software consultant for 6 years now. I&amp;rsquo;ve worked with all sorts of clients: small businesses, non profits, individuals, and even large enterprise organizations. Admittedly, this is just a drop in the bucket over the span of an entire career, but during this time I&amp;rsquo;ve learned a ton.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Lately, I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking a lot about about what it takes to have happy clients. I have great relationships with my clients because of three things: communication, responsiveness, and honesty. I know, it sounds super cheesy, I know. But these to me have been more important than the work itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong, the actual work you do is very important. &lt;em&gt;Do the best damn job you can.&lt;/em&gt; Seriously. However, giving yourself the space to do a good job is accomplished by being honest about what it&amp;rsquo;s going to take. It&amp;rsquo;s about communicating issues properly so you and your client can find solutions together.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;Communication&lt;/h3&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;As an expert in your field, it&amp;rsquo;s up to you to translate technical/advanced concepts into terms that non-technical folks can understand. They&amp;rsquo;re hiring you not only to do the job, but to communicate clearly what you&amp;rsquo;re doing.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Communication is about guidance. Give your clients enough information to make decisions on their own. Don&amp;rsquo;t just tell them why doing something is bad, help them understand &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;. I can&amp;rsquo;t stand when developers say &amp;ldquo;We can&amp;rsquo;t do it because it&amp;rsquo;s the wrong way.&amp;rdquo; What&amp;rsquo;s obvious to you may not be obvious to the client. Take the time to talk about tradeoffs, costs, and timelines so clients can decide what&amp;rsquo;s best for their business.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Similarly, if they&amp;rsquo;re requesting something to be built or designed &amp;ndash; dig deeper. Find out what the core problem is, and see if you can work together to find a better way to solve it.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Doing this is hard. It takes practice. But it&amp;rsquo;s well worth it. When you&amp;rsquo;re able to effectively translate your knowledge about a problem or project, you&amp;rsquo;re bringing the client into the process and helping them make an informed decision.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;Responsiveness&lt;/h3&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;This one is so damn easy. I don&amp;rsquo;t understand why people aren&amp;rsquo;t better at this. So much of the fear of hiring a developer or a freelancer is that they&amp;rsquo;ll go silent when there are questions that need to be answered.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;It makes sense. People want to know you&amp;rsquo;re available, that you&amp;rsquo;re not going to just disappear with all their money. They&amp;rsquo;re putting a lot of trust into you by agreeing to work with you. If you get an email, slack message, text, call, whatever &amp;ndash; just respond. That&amp;rsquo;s it. If you don&amp;rsquo;t know the answer, say &amp;ldquo;Let me check it out and get back to you.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s so much better than silence. When you&amp;rsquo;re absoutely silent, you build resentment. By the end of the project, there is a much lower chance the client will be happy and want to work with you again.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;Honesty&lt;/h3&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Being straight up with your clients (and prospective clients) is the best way to build trust. It lets them know you&amp;rsquo;re not just going to agree to anything they request, and that you really have their best interests at heart.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Sometimes when someone comes to me with an idea, I point them to a solution that doesn&amp;rsquo;t involve me at all. Things like showing them how to create an awesome onboarding process using &lt;a href="http://www.typeform.com/"&gt;Typeform&lt;/a&gt;, or telling them that &lt;a href="https://www.squarespace.com/"&gt;Squarespace&lt;/a&gt; can be a beautiful solution for what they&amp;rsquo;re looking for. Or that &lt;a href="https://www.shopify.com/"&gt;Shopify&lt;/a&gt; can be set up by someone with no coding experience at all. All of these tools have a ton of themes and add-ons that require no additional coding to manage. Often, the right answer is &amp;ldquo;You probably shouldn&amp;rsquo;t pay me a bunch of money to build something that you could get online for cheap, if not free.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Other times, people will come to me with extremely unrealistic expectations. They might want to build a massive application within a month. Well, the reality of it is that while we could get &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; out in a month, it won&amp;rsquo;t be good. And they&amp;rsquo;ll definitely end up paying for it down the line.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;In both of these cases, I&amp;rsquo;d rather turn down the project or send back a realistic estimate, even if it&amp;rsquo;s not exactly what the client originally wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Most of this stuff is pretty common sense. Building a good relationship is easy. Be a good communicator, be responsive and be honest. Over time, you&amp;rsquo;ll build up trust. If your clients trust you, they&amp;rsquo;ll be more open to your input on projects. They&amp;rsquo;ll be more open to referring work to you. They&amp;rsquo;ll do everything they can to help you be successful, since you&amp;rsquo;ve already done the same for them.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;As an expert, our skills are temporary. Half of our knowledge becomes obselete every few years. However, as a consultant, as a collaborator &amp;ndash; the necessary skills don&amp;rsquo;t change. That&amp;rsquo;s why it&amp;rsquo;s really important to constantly practice them and get it right.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Comments? Questions? Drop me a line at &lt;a href="mailto:hello@graybike.co"&gt;hello@graybike.co&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <title>Getting better at project estimation</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/words/2015-11-15-getting-better-at-project-estimation/"/>
        <id>http://blog.url.com/words/2015-11-15-getting-better-at-project-estimation/</id>
        <published>2015-11-14T19:00:00-05:00</published>
        <updated>2017-09-19T16:09:05-04:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Article Author</name>
        </author>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;How many times have you started a project with some kind of assumption on the project duration, and how many times have you found that to be off? Pretty much everyone gets it wrong. What we can do to be better about it?&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;One notorious example of this in the US was the development of the &lt;a href="https://www.healthcare.gov/"&gt;healthcare.gov&lt;/a&gt; website. Originally, the project was estimated to cost &lt;a href="http://uk.reuters.com/article/2013/10/17/uk-usa-healthcare-technology-insight-idUKBRE99G06120131017"&gt;about $93.7 million&lt;/a&gt;, but the final cost &lt;a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2014-09-24/obamacare-website-costs-exceed-2-billion-study-finds"&gt;exceeded $2 billion dollars&lt;/a&gt;. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t really matter who is to blame for that drastic underestimation. My only point here is: whether a project is small or large, estimating cost is hard. Really hard. And almost everyone is likely to get at least part of it wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to explore a few things that go wrong when estimating projects. Not everything thing here may apply to you, but hopefully you&amp;rsquo;ll find it at least some of it useful. Above all, I hope to provide a perspective for makers on where they could potentially go wrong when making estimates.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;How does it work?&lt;/h3&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Typically, when a developer or designer estimates a project, she might do a few things:&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Ask a few questions about the project and try to learn a bit more.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Try to break the overall project down into smaller pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Confer with a few other folks and play &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planning_poker"&gt;&amp;ldquo;planning poker&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Think about times where she&amp;rsquo;s built something similar before and try to remember how long it took.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the estimate is usually needed in a short amount of time. She will have to take a shot in the dark to put some numbers together. She probably figures any inaccuracies can be made up by burning the midnight oil. The strange part is she&amp;rsquo;s likely pretty confident about being able to deliver the project on time, even though she doesn&amp;rsquo;t have much concrete evidence to prove the estimate will be accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;This confidence comes from being overly optimistic, a type of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optimism_bias"&gt;congitive bias&lt;/a&gt;. But I&amp;rsquo;ll get more into that later. First, a story:&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;In Daniel Kahneman&amp;rsquo;s excellent book, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0374533555"&gt;Thinking, Fast and Slow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, he talks a lot about the psychology behind congitive biases. He describes an example where he and a small team were designing a curriculum to teach decision making to high school students. After working for one year (and making great progress), his team got together to estimate the remaining time to complete the project. They predicted that the project would take two years to complete. The project ended up taking eight years to finish.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;The outside view&lt;/h3&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;When estimating projects, people often fail to take into consideration a baseline prediction to use as a comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Essentially, this concept is the fact that when estimating projects, we fail to consider what other similar projects (the &amp;ldquo;outside view&amp;rdquo;) took to complete. To make the estimate, we draw solely upon the evidence right in front of us (the &amp;ldquo;inside view&amp;rdquo;) to make a judgement. This approach often fails due to a lack of actual evidence from similar projects.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;For many projects, not everyone has a baseline to compare to when trying to estimate a project. That&amp;rsquo;s why clients go to the experts (that&amp;rsquo;s us) to figure things out. The experts have worked on many projects like this and have a wide range of examples to draw from.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;This is where it gets interesting. Of Kahneman&amp;rsquo;s team working on the curriculum, most of the members did not have prior experience working on a similar project, nor did they know of other projects they could compare. However, one member of the project did know about other similar projects, and how long they took. Yet, even though he did have this larger data set to draw on, he ignored it and made his first prediction based on his experience in the projet thus far and intuition. &lt;strong&gt;He consciously ignored evidence that would help him estimate his project better.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Only once he was asked a pointed question about how other projects of the type fared did he come up with an accurate estiamte.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;This happens pretty often. To quote Kahneman:&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is common pattern: people who have information about an individual case rarely feel the need to know the statistics of a class to which the case belongs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;We tend take the first and easiest piece of evidence (the project we&amp;rsquo;ve been involved in), and we never bother to look for additional evidence. It&amp;rsquo;s sometimes referred to as &lt;a href="https://www.brainpickings.org/2014/08/27/willful-blindness-margaret-heffernan/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;willful blindness&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;: we instinctively ignore evidence even when it&amp;rsquo;s right in front of us.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;Optimism Bias&lt;/h3&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Often when estimating projects, developers and designers tend to think in &amp;ldquo;best case&amp;rdquo; terms when estimating projects. How long will the authentication system take to build? Probably just a few hours. How soon can I get the entire onboarding flow mocked up? Probably a day, two days max.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;More often than not, we simply ignore any chance of mishap or project delay, and we assume the best for estimation. Even if we &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; we&amp;rsquo;re assuming the worst, we probably aren&amp;rsquo;t. We don&amp;rsquo;t consider the fact that statistically speaking, it&amp;rsquo;s very unlikely that we&amp;rsquo;ll breeze through a project without any setbacks.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;Avoiding the planning fallacy&lt;/h3&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;The two pitfalls described above are part of what is known as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planning_fallacy"&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Planning Fallacy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. In other words, it&amp;rsquo;s a matter of being too optimistic about a timeline, and ignoring evidence available to us indicating otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;To counter the &amp;ldquo;inside view&amp;rdquo;, we need to understand our instinctive first guess may not always be completely accurate. That first guess isn&amp;rsquo;t taking into account any of the unknowns, and we need to spend time researching what those could be. When we approach estimation with an analytical eye, looking for evidence to support our idea of how long something will take, we&amp;rsquo;re more likely to land on an accurate estimate. Yes, this may take longer to come up with some accurate numbers &amp;ndash; but it&amp;rsquo;s well worth it. It&amp;rsquo;s better to invest the time up front and mitigate our risk for delays down the line.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first 90 percent of the code accounts for the first 90 percent of the development time. The remaining 10 percent of the code accounts for the other 90 percent of the development time.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Tom Cargill, Bell Labs&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;We humans tend to think things will go better for us than they do for others. Unfortunately, it&amp;rsquo;s pretty unlikely. It&amp;rsquo;s important to bake in room for error &amp;amp; delays. When putting together an estimate, I always add in about 20 percent time as room for delay. If I&amp;rsquo;m able to finish ahead of schedule, it gives me room to add polish to make the project that much better. If nothing else, I can launch early! But, if something does delay the project, I&amp;rsquo;ve got a bit of padding to make sure it still gets out on time.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;Diving Deeper&lt;/h3&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Project estimation is a matter of doing your due diligence. I view project estimation as starting the design/discovery phase early. Before we can produce any concrete numbers, we need to do some work up front. Mock up some wireframes to understand the interaction better. Ask lots of questions about behavior, and try to get into specifics. Think of edge cases and all possible scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;A good project proposal &amp;amp; estimate has the added benefit of acting as a project plan.  When you&amp;rsquo;ve gone to such great lengths to understand a project before coming up with an estimate, you&amp;rsquo;re much more accurate and likely to predict challenges. Project research &amp;amp; planning should be the first phase of a project. When it&amp;rsquo;s done, there is a concrete deliverable of research and a more accurate view of timelines.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;Break down components, not time&lt;/h3&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Try to break things down as small as you can when estimating. It leaves less room for error, and it makes it much easier to find examples of other projects doing the same thing. It&amp;rsquo;s very helpful to get as granular as possible when planning. Of course, this takes time. There&amp;rsquo;s usually a lot of communication between designer &amp;amp; client to hash out the smaller details before an accurate estimate can be put forth.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;However, one thing that is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; useful is trying to estimate in small units of time (hours). It&amp;rsquo;s much easier to come up with an accurate estimate when you&amp;rsquo;re dealing with a matter of days (preferably weeks). As designer &lt;a href="http://alistapart.com/column/creating-accurate-estimates"&gt;Matt Griffin mentions&lt;/a&gt; describes, there&amp;rsquo;s a huge difference between a productive hour vs. a wasted hour. The difference averages out when we think in days or weeks instead of hours.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;Track your time meticulously&lt;/h3&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t stress this enough. Diligently tracking your time helps you understand exactly how long it takes to finish a task. It&amp;rsquo;s a great way to look back and know how close you were to your original estimate. You&amp;rsquo;ll know the breakdown of time between meetings, writing code, designing, etc. Over time, you&amp;rsquo;ll build your own little database of projects to use as a baseline for how long a project may take you.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;Adjust scope, not schedule&lt;/h3&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll get a client that says &amp;ldquo;we really need this project done a month earlier&amp;rdquo;, and you think to yourself, &amp;ldquo;maybe I can just work nights &amp;amp; weekends and pull this off&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Even if you manage to work day and night to pull off a project, the quality of your work will suffer drastically because you&amp;rsquo;ll burn yourself out. More often, work will compound and you&amp;rsquo;ll realize you have more work left to do, and you&amp;rsquo;ll have to delay the project.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Committing to an unreasonable schedule is disingenuous. It&amp;rsquo;s damaging to you, your client, and the project. The art of project estimation sometimes involves saying no. It&amp;rsquo;s your job as the expert to convey the true cost of building things.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s better to be realistic early on in a project and cut out the fat rather than realize you&amp;rsquo;re going to miss your launch after you&amp;rsquo;ve announced it to the whole world.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;Estimation is collaboration&lt;/h3&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Project estimation should be a collaborative process. Both you and the client should be heavily involved in the estimation phase. It gives opportunity to learn about the project and discover nuances that would normally get overlooked when the process is one-sided. It allows for client input and feedback, and gives both parties a view into what it will be like to work together.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Obviously, doing this takes time (are you sick of hearing me say this yet?). Giving project estimation the importance and space it needs will result in a more accurate estimate, a better project, and a happier working relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;I work with a lot of companies to help them plan their projects and build products. If you&amp;rsquo;d like some help planning your next project, &lt;a href="mailto:hello@graybike.co"&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear from you&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;P.S. Much thanks to &lt;a href="http://pbj.me/"&gt;Patrick Johnson&lt;/a&gt; for editing this post. Go check out his work.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <title>Working while traveling (or the other way around)</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/words/2015-11-10-working-while-traveling/"/>
        <id>http://blog.url.com/words/2015-11-10-working-while-traveling/</id>
        <published>2015-11-09T19:00:00-05:00</published>
        <updated>2017-09-19T16:09:05-04:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Article Author</name>
        </author>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was originally posted on the &lt;a href="http://blog.hellohummings.com/post/132694922089/working-while-traveling-or-the-other-way-around"&gt;Hummings blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;GET WORK&lt;/h3&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;First of all, find work that can be done remotely. This can be anything from being a virtual assistant, designer, developer, project manager, etc. I’m an engineer so as long as I have a laptop, wifi, and an outlet I’m good to go. There are tons of possibilities, and you don’t always have to be a freelancer to do it. Many companies (&lt;a href="https://weworkremotely.com/"&gt;weworkremotely.com&lt;/a&gt;) allow their employees to work remotely, as long as they get their stuff done.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;GET OUT&lt;/h3&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Ultimately, when you’re traveling, you’re not working, and when you’re working, you’re not traveling. When you’re exploring the maze of small cobblestone streets of Fez, it’s unlikely you’re going to be getting any meaningful work done. Likewise, if you’re focused on your laptop screen, you’re not going to be taking in your surroundings or connecting with local culture. It’s unrealistic to expect you will, and trying to do so will only make you stressed out and unhappy.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;You need to give yourself the space to work without distraction. When I went to Mexico City and Oaxaca, I worked full time and got quite a bit done while traveling because I made time for both work and travel. It doesn’t matter where you decide to work, whether you’re in your hotel or on a sandy beach. In fact, it’s probably better in your hotel – where there’s electricity, a strong wifi signal, and most importantly – a quiet place to focus. Then, when your work is completed, you can go explore without worrying about whether you’re working or handling your responsibilities. Finding time to separate work and exploration/travel is extremely important. Set aside days where you know you’ll be working that day, and don’t expect to go check out that local market that you’ve heard about. Instead, set aside time tomorrow, over the weekend, or next week when you know you can go explore without feeling guilty.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Doing things this way also means you need to be in places for longer than you would if you were there on a 10 day vacation. My favorite place to travel was Morocco. I didn’t work full time while I was there, but it was an amazing place. A one month trip to Morocco (if you’re planning on working full time) isn’t really enough to explore the country on a deep level. In a one month trip, if you’re working until the evenings and exploring on weekends, that only gives you about 8 full days of exploring, not counting evenings. In the evenings, there may be times where you’re tired from working all day, and just want to relax – and that’s OK.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve found that it works best if you have at least three months in a place. That gives you enough auxiliary days to explore and you won’t feel the pressure of having to maximize every single second so that you don’t miss anything. Trying to do too much in too little time can be extremely stressful and will undoubtedly lead to burnout. You can have downtime, you can explore things, and still have enough time to work as you’re expected.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;STAY CONNECTED&lt;/h3&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Stay connected. I can’t emphasize this enough. Most countries will allow you to buy a sim card with data. This will, at the very least, provide you with access to email and instant messaging if you need to stay in touch with your clients and coworkers. In a pinch you can even use the data access to turn your phone into a hotspot so you can access the data with your computer. You never know if a cafe is going to have reliable internet before you arrive – having a backup plan in place is a great way to mitigate that.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Do your research beforehand. In Mexico, the coworking spots had amazingly fast internet, but unfortunately in Oaxaca they did not – I ended up going to cafes a lot there. If you’re going to a city, try to find where you’d be able to work, and make sure to reach out to the hostel, hotel, or Airbnb and ask them about internet speeds. Tell people you need to work from your room and will need high-speed internet – people are usually pretty up front about whether that’d be feasible from their hotels or not.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Sometimes you need to arrive in a place a few days before you start work just so that you can explore cafes or coworking spaces to find the ones that make for a good working environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;BE RESPONSIVE&lt;/h3&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;The biggest concern for clients, employers, or anyone else you work with is that when you finally get off that plane and start exploring the Guatemalan mountains, you’ll be impossible to reach. Something goes wrong and someone has a question, and they’ll just get your auto response email or your voicemail and things will all go awry. Regularly checking email, responding to messaging, and returning calls can instill confidence in those that work with you, and assuage their concerns about you being on a different continent.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;If you know you’re going to be offline for a few days – tell people. Let them know that it’s only for a short time and you’ll be back on the case soon – people are usually very understanding about such things. I like being transparent about all aspects of my business so when I told my clients that I would be working while traveling, they all took it pretty well because I’ve established a habit of regular communication with them. I’ve been working remotely with all of them for a long time now. Ultimately it’s a matter of trust – you need to promise to stay in touch and work hard, and they need to believe you. You also need to follow through on that promise.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;MANAGE YOUR TIME&lt;/h3&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Try an alternate schedule. I find I work best in the mornings before lunch. This is my focused, uncluttered time since my mind is fresh and hasn’t been inundated with emails, stresses, and other things that seep into one’s brain on a daily basis. Then, I like to explore for a few hours in the afternoon while it’s still light out, and then I continue to work in the evening/nighttime.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Try alternating the days you explore – spend Sunday working and go to the touristy location on a Tuesday when it’s less crowded. Maybe waking up really early in the morning and working until 2 PM is the way you want to go, giving you the remainder of the day to explore without worrying about work.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Try different things and see which one works for you.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;LIVE, DON’T TRAVEL&lt;/h3&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Try approaching things from the perspective of living instead of traveling. Go to the local markets, buy groceries, and cook at home (eating out adds up FAST when you’re traveling). Find out where you can do laundry. Know the cafes that are good to work from. Meet your neighbors. Try to enjoy the environment you’re in, rather than frantically trying to check items off of a list and just really soak in your surroundings.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Obviously exploring the tourist attractions is fun and you should balance that with everything else. However, living instead of traveling will save you money, lower your stress levels, and allow for a deeper connection with the local culture.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content>
      </entry>
    </feed>
    <footer id='footer'>
      <ul class='text-center'>
        <li>
          <p>
            <a href='mailto:hello@graybike.co'>hello@graybike.co</a>
          </p>
        </li>
        <li class='divider'>
          <p>&#xb7;</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>415.326.3397</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </footer>
    <script>
      !function(){var e=document.body,t=(document.documentElement,Math.max(e.offsetHeight,0)),n=Math.max(document.documentElement.clientHeight,window.innerHeight||0),o=document.getElementById("footer");n>t&&(o.style.position="absolute")}();
    </script>
    <script src="../javascripts/all.js" type="text/javascript"></script>
    <!-- Google Analytics -->
    <script>
      (function(i,s,o,g,r,a,m){i['GoogleAnalyticsObject']=r;i[r]=i[r]||function(){
        (i[r].q=i[r].q||[]).push(arguments)},i[r].l=1*new Date();a=s.createElement(o),
        m=s.getElementsByTagName(o)[0];a.async=1;a.src=g;m.parentNode.insertBefore(a,m)
      })(window,document,'script','//www.google-analytics.com/analytics.js','ga');
      
      ga('create', 'UA-51459213-1', 'graybike.co');
      ga('send', 'pageview');
    </script>
  </body>
</html>
